If tomorrow somebody finds even a
classical factoring algorithm in
polinomial time, I think there'll be
chaos in the world.
>> This is Avi Wigerson Turing award and
Abel Prize winner and I interviewed him
all about his field.
>> The question of P versus ZP is whether
we can solve all the problems we really
want to solve. The quality of randomness
is in the eye of the beholder or in the
computational power of the beholder. How
can anybody convince me that they have a
proof of P different than NP? And
nevertheless, I know absolutely nothing
about the way they proved it. And it
turns out they can do it for the
wholeing problem. For problems that are
not computable, you know, if tomorrow
somebody finds an efficient algorithm
for NP complete problems, you know what
do you do?
>> Here's the full episode.
In one of your lectures, you mentioned
that P= NP is philosophically about the
fundamental limits of human knowledge.
What is P= NP and how does it relate to
human knowledge?
>> Well, in the simplest way and I will
talk at the high level. Uh we are
interested in various problems in life
in all sorts of problems, mathematical
problems, scientific problems, medical
problems, personal problems,
intellectual problems. We are in the
business in computer science of solving
problems by computers. Now uh we would
like to somehow classify
uh those problems that we can solve
right to know what we can know. Well,
the problems we can solve are the things
we will know, we will understand. So,
there are all the problems that we want
to understand. There are many of them.
Uh, and the problems that we can
understand, can solve. Okay. In a very
basic way, the first class is NP. All
the problems we want to solve are really
NP problems. So, it's a class of
problems.
uh a subset of it is the problems we can
solve. They're the problems we can
currently solve. But we are interested
in all the problems we can solve in
principle we can ever you know really
solve. So the question of P versus NP is
whether we can solve all the problems we
really want to solve. Whether we can
know everything we want to know.
This is basically about the limits of
our knowledge. Of course, I have to
justify why you know these classes which
are mathematically defined actually are
captured by this intuitive
u intuitive meanings I'm giving them. P
is very easy to justify what we can
solve is what we can uh you know solve
in our lifetime using whatever we have
let's say all computers that we uh have
using efficient algorithms. So problems
we can solve are problems you see in our
apps in our phones, right? If there's a
navigation app, it means somebody
invented an algorithm that's efficient
enough to solve any, you know, shortest
path problem between any two places in
any kind of map.
Okay. Uh where all the problems we want
to solve are NP problems.
What is NP? NP is a class of problem.
the mathematical definition
uh problems so that you know whether
they are easy or hard to solve we don't
know but if somebody hands us a solution
then we can easily check that indeed it
is a good solution now why are all
problems we humanity is interested in of
this nature you can think there's no
limit to what we may want to know but I
claim that essentially in any human
endeavor
The
if you are embarking on any problem, if
you really seriously want to solve a
problem, the least you want to know is
that when you hit upon a solution,
you'll recognize it as a solution. And
why would you ever start on looking for
something if you will never recognize it
as what you looked for? So you think
mathematicians are looking for proofs of
theorems. Certainly if somebody gives a
proof you know wrote a paper about it we
can verify if a scientist wants to
explain data
uh you know about the planets or about I
don't know
bacteria or whatever uh you know want to
develop a theory so that's what we are
searching for in this case and yeah we
again scientists write papers about
their theories have to be consistent
with the data We have a way of of
recognizing that this is a good
solution. Engineers
uh you know are usually tasked with
creating something bridge or phone or
you know something uh under some
constraints. It can be monetary
constraints, physical constraints, all
sorts of you can use this but not this
and so on. Anyway, if an engineer
designed something, whoever gave them
the task can look at it and say, "Well,
you you violated some constraints." Oh,
no, it's good. You you you really
delivered what we were looking for. So,
I'm giving you examples. I mean, I can
give many more. Detectives are supposed
to solve crimes and you know, we know
from detective books, you know, they
eventually provide them. So these are
examples of uh very fundamental human
endeavors that are you know encompass
almost everything I can think of. In all
of them what people are searching for
have the property that when a solution
is found it is easily recognized.
So
repeating in the beginning NP are all
problems that we can honestly say we
really want to solve and P are those
that we can solve. whether they are
equal. You know, if they are equal, then
everything we would want to know, cure
for cancer,
uh you know, anything you imagine uh can
be, you know, just the very fact that
a solution can be easily recognized
would imply that it can be efficiently
found. That means that we can know
everything we ever want to know. It's a
fundamental question about human
knowledge.
So, I know this is one of those um
Millennium Prize problems. There's a
million-dollar prize if you can provide
a proof for for this. You know, I can
imagine you could prove that they're
equivalent. You could also prove that
they're not. If you had to guess like
when and if a proof comes, which
direction would your intuition say it
goes and why? I think that my intuition
and that's probably hold for almost all
members of the theoretical
computer science community is that they
are different. I think there are several
reasons for that and I will already tell
you now that they you know they are not
that convincing. [laughter]
One is I think intuition that most of us
have that you know finding something is
really hard and just checking that it's
there. If you lost your keys or your
phone and you know you have no idea
where to look but you know somebody
points out oh you left it on the window
seal or something like this. Yes. Ah
yeah I did. So we have this uh
experience from life that finding is
typically a harder task than just
checking that it is what we look for.
Another is that
real NP problems occur all over the
place. occur in optimization, in logic,
in other aspects in mathematics, in
verifying that algorithms and protocols
and security systems actually work all
sorts of uh and
uh in this generality these optimization
problems that are NP problems maybe NP
hard problems uh people try to solve for
completely
you know egocentric to make their
company richer or to uh and there are
thousands of these and they have they
manifest themselves in many different
forms and so over the maybe
50 60 70 years. Uh people seriously look
for algorithms for these very different
ones and couldn't find any.
This you know may seem like there's no
such solution
and in a uh getting a bit more technical
u NP problems NP complete problems in
particular are uh seem to require search
over an exponential exponentially large
space
like all the all the possible uh you
know solutions to some u system of
equations for example
and uh somehow P versus NP is about
having a general method for cutting down
this exponentially search space into
searching over something much smaller in
a clever way and this should apply to
all these problems so that would be P
equal NP and people don't think that
there is such a way but as I said you
know these are
uh yeah these are intuitions that are
you know maybe pretty strong and uh yeah
I think that's the only you know if
tomorrow somebody finds an algorithm for
an efficient algorithm for complete
problems using some new idea that nobody
ever thought of you know what do you do
[laughter]
>> that would change the world in software
engineering we we use algorithms all the
time and they often have these very
satisfying properties where the solution
you know we we use space or some
algorithm that can take something where
the brute force is uh something much
larger to down to something that's
polomial time or something very
reasonable but in all these NP problems
it's pretty unsatisfying that the best
we could do is brute force is am I
understanding that correctly
>> yeah you're yeah you're understanding it
perfectly correctly. I think that maybe
what you are getting at is that
NPcomplete problems are you know a
particular NP complete problem is really
a family of instances right I mean you
want to to find the Hamiltonian tour
some traveling salesman to through
through some map you know there's this
map and that map and this network and
other network and you know there are
many many instances when we talk about
an algorithm for them. Typically we say
an algorithm is efficient if it's
efficient and correct on all of them.
In software engineering and many aspects
of uh you know optimization in many uh
real world problems the instances is a
much more restricted set.
you know they come from uh you know
trying to verify a particular protocol
or
I don't know protein folding if you want
to think about the biological example uh
the way it is phrased as an NP uh hard
problem is
you want to minimize the energy of a
system under some various constraints
which have to relate to the chemistry of
the various uh molecules and atoms
appear in in the protein. [snorts] Uh
and this kind of optimization problem
one can easily prove is np hard and
nevertheless our body faults our
proteins all the time you know in
extremely efficiently. Now why is that?
Of course, I don't know really why is
that, but it would seem that evolution
uh designed proteins in such a way that
this, you know, folding them only them.
We don't have that many proteins. There
are not exponentially many proteins in
the body. There are only a few that
maybe are more prone to efficient energy
minimization. So uh and more generally I
think in software engineer you or at
least in verification and testing you
often want to check that something meets
the specifications.
Uh you usually translate it into a
satisfiability
uh question of bulan formulas. the
formulas that you get or the instances
that you get out of these uh have some
structure and may maybe for them various
greedy approaches or clever not just
greedy but clever uh but efficient
methods work. In other words is making
it short uh instances that come up are
not the worst case instances. We have
many examples of this that we can
actually prove this. For example, early
on it was recognized that uh the simplex
method which is an algorithm to solve
linear programs
uh on the one hand uh requires
exponential time for you know worst case
system of inequalities.
Uh but uh in practice it seems to run in
linear time. So evidently the sets of
linear systems that we tackle in real
life are you know have some extra
structure that allow this particular
algorithm to uh to solve them
efficiently. Of course, today we know an
algorithm that's efficient for all in
our programs, but it's much more
complicated and people don't or I don't
know how much it's used in practice, but
the simplex method is a very simple to
run and yeah, usually it works. You
mentioned the protein folding and I mean
yeah that's an interesting one because
it's it's an NP problem but it was
solved to a acceptable extent and you
when I was reading about it it it wasn't
solved for 100% of cases it provides a
solution and a confidence score but it
doesn't give you the answer 100%
accurate you fully computed and so when
you think about these NP P problems.
What if you relaxed the the criteria of
being correct? Could the asmtoic
complexity be less than the exponential
that we're talking about?
>> Yeah, it's a very natural and good
problem. So in the in the uh protein
folding you were talking about alpha
fold I guess which is an algorithm a
uristic
that was learned from existing proteins
and uh is working very well on you know
on instances it didn't see but are still
proteins coming from the body even if it
did perfectly on these not just that
would still be for in the discussion I
mentioned before because the instances
it is trying to sort of come from real
life and probably have extra structure
that allow efficient solution. But you
are right there. That's one of the
things that people naturally do when
they cannot solve a an optimization
problem exactly because it's NP complete
or NP hard. Maybe I should say NP
complete NP out problems are those
problems in NP that are are as hard as
all problems in NP. If you solve one
efficiently, you solved all efficiently.
If you prove one hard then you proved
all of them hard. So they somehow
capture the complexity of the class and
traveling salesman is an example and
protein fodic in this framework of
energy minimization is one and
banability and so on. Okay. So you want
to optimize something and it's np
complete np hard. Uh so that's a sign
that you shouldn't try to find an
algorithm that works always. But one
thing you can do is do an approximation.
That's a very natural relaxation. You
don't want the optimum. You are willing
to live with a factor of two from
optimum or 10% from optimum or some
factor away from optimum.
Uh
NP completeness was discovered in the
early 70s. In the early 90s there was a
breakthrough called the PCP theorem. The
PCPCOM allows you to argue hardness of
even approximation problems.
So for example you can show that uh uh
satisfiability of banan formulas
um you know it's not just so you you
want to meet you want to let's say find
an assignment to a bunch of constraints
let's say bulam constraints let's say on
three variables for simplicity
uh so you want to satisfy all of them uh
the the relaxation would be Okay, I want
to satisfy 90% of them or as good a
fraction as I can. if I cannot get 100%
of them the PCP theorem one way to
phrase it and certainly one of the
consequence major consequence is that we
know that you cannot even achieve a very
good approximation and to illustrate how
uh uh you know tight this understanding
is for some problems is that for the
example I gave when there are only three
variables per constraint if you just
guess at random the values to the
variables in the assignment you will
satisfy uh 78 of the constraints. This
is because each particular constraint is
usually the disjunction of three
variables will be true with probability
it's an or three will be with
probability 78. So if you random if you
don't think don't look at the formula
even you can satisfy
78 of them and the PCP theorem and
significant strengthening by hustad
hustad tells you that if you want to
satisfy 78 plus epsilon
that's already npr
so we know today to argue the difficulty
not only of finding the perfect solution
the optim optimal solution. But even uh
how close to optimal you can get uh for
lots and lots of problems large classes
of problems in particular constraint
optimization problems uh you know of the
type of such fabric. So even if you
solve just the slightest epsilon for any
trivially small epsilon,
>> it's just as hard as doing the full
>> as hard as finding the optimum. So
>> you mentioned uh MP hard, nplete, you
know, NP. I know there's other
complexity classes. Maybe you could give
some more context on kind of the whole
space of complexity classes.
>> Yeah. So uh I'm just remark that uh we
have a zoo of complexity classes and in
fact there's a website called uh yeah
the complexity zoo which has in it
hundreds of uh hundreds and hundreds of
complexity classes of all types
websites started by Scott Arson once we
realized that there he realizes
there's a whole zoo out there we want to
know the relationship between these
classes. Okay. So what uh what is the
point about these classes? Uh like P and
NP we want to classify problems by the
amount of resources they take. So P
polinomial time is a class of problem
that can be solved in an amount of time
that relates polomially to the size of
the data. Of course you expect that you
the data there's more data the instance
grows you'll spend more time but if it's
you know linear time or quadic time or
cubic time you say let me call it at
least theoretically efficient
and uh uh np uh you classify not the
time to solve but the time to verify a
solution if it was given you want this
to be a polomial time. So it's a very
different but uh first of all there are
you know many more time functions that
just polomial and exponential and uh and
you know doubly exponential and you can
go to finite and uh uh you know one
fundamental result starting with
Turing's paper is that there are
problems that are simply unsolvable by
computers. So really the first comp
complexity class is a class of solvable
problems, decidable problems to ensure
that these are not all problems. There
are natural problems that are not
decidable at all. But time is only one
resource and uh we are interested and
you know both from practical and
theoretical reasons in lots of other
resources. Memory is a resource costly
resource and we want to minimize space.
the space invested in in a computation
uh in in problems with several parties.
You are interested in the amount of
communication exchange. So not the
internal computational
effort that they exert themselves but
how much you know if you talk to a
satellite you want to minimize the
communication. You can think about
energy. You can think about uh yeah
there there are plenty of your parallel
time. How much can you speed up you know
computation of a problem if you work on
it not with one computer but with n
computers if you your data is of size
then you know does it you know allow it
to solve it immediately or maybe it
doesn't help at all. So there are
complexity classes
classify problems according to how much
resources they need and there are many
of these and one important part of so
that's a a major theme in the
methodology of comp complex complexity
theory and uh coming with it is uh
attempts to understand complexity
classes
as problems that relate to each other
even if you don't know their complexity.
So for example, MP is a class and we
don't know the complexity of all
problems in this or MP complete
problems. We don't know whether they are
all easy or or hard but we do know we
have efficient algorithms to translate
one into the other.
So it's not obvious that if you want to
uh solve a satisfiability problem you
don't know how but you have an algorithm
to solve sudoku problems
uh without not just 3x3 but also 4 by if
you had a an efficient method to solve
sudoku problems P equals NP because you
can efficiently take an instance of
subscribability or so salesman or
factoring integer or any of these
problems be from it the sudoku problem
and from the solution of the sudoku
problem you can translate back and get
the best solution for your original I
know traveling salesman tool so we are
interested in uh efficient reductions
between problems whose complexity we
don't know but we want to relate them to
each other we build some kind of partial
order of the hardness of uh different
problems. So there yeah really yeah you
don't want to know how many uh problems
we have some arise for constraints that
the real world maybe technology
imposes or cause for and some are
naturally arising mathematically because
you know they're interesting.
>> You mentioned that these NPcomplete
problems they kind of are all equivalent
in some way. What's the the proof to you
know equate a SAT solving problem to
like a graph coloring problem or
something like that? Are they all
similar in nature or are they kind of
bespoke to you know the problem you're
going to and from? is a very good
question and uh uh you will find that in
most of these they call them reductions
algorithms to translate one problem to
another uh most of them are relatively
simple and uh not all and I talked about
the PCP theorem before showing that
approximation is is all this is very
highly non trivial but most computers
proof like between coloring and satis
satisfiability and it goes both ways.
They are both complete. So it goes both
ways. It is simple and the first one
uh was the satisfiability problem. The
you know original papers of cook and
leaven defining NP completeness and
proving that NP complete problems exist.
They both uh the first problem they push
complete was satisfiability.
Why is this? So why can all these other
problems be reduced to satisfiability?
The reason is really that computation is
local.
Uh
computation is local. I mean that if you
think about your computer, your laptop
or any any computational device, usually
it manipulates bits uh uh by some local
operations. You look at this these two
registers and you add them or you take
these two bits and exclusive all them or
end them or something and you will do a
sequence of this sequence of simple
operations and you arrive at a
conclusion. This locality can be
translated
to
uh a bunch of constraints or what would
be consistent sequence of states of your
machine. If you look at the time
evolution of any computation, you know,
memories in some state then in another
state and but they change locally. Okay.
So if you had the if you could guess and
that's the NP part. I mean if somebody
provided you the table of computation,
you could check that it's consistent by
writing a bunch of local constraints. So
you know some conjunction of very few
variables
uh
uh on all over this table of computation
uh and write down a satisfiability
problem. I want this to be true and this
to be true and this to be true for some
assignment and what does the assignment
has to satisfy it should be a table like
this all these constraints should be
satisfi you know should be true and
it has to be consistent with the input
given right so some of the input has to
match the first time zero uh content of
the of the machine so this locality uh
allows for many of these translations.
If you realize this, you will quickly
find a reduction from coloring to satis.
It's also I mean it's not clear why
coloring is an evolution of computation
but it's starts already by local
constraints. you want a few colors and
that every so some in some it's even
easier but uh um the reduction from any
NP computation that's that's what NP
computers means anything in NP can be
translated to satisfiability NP is just
a computation of a touring machine say
uh only that you don't know what is a
computation if somebody guessed it or
showed it to you then you all you need
is to verify this verification is local
and that's the source of many simple uh
you know uh MP completeness reductions
let let me give you a a really simple
example why why uh is factoring integers
reducible to
uh satisfiability
because if I gave you factors of an
integer you could just multiply them and
check that they equal the input. This
multiplication is a is a simple
algorithm, right? I mean, we know how to
do it from second grade or something. Uh
you write down the computation of
multiplication in this local way and all
you need is that uh somebody will guess
for you really the factors. You
mentioned time complexity and space
complexity and I think intuitively like
in software engineering we often trade
those off for each other. Is there uh
like general theory on that on how these
two trade off?
>> Yeah. Yeah. We have uh yeah all these
questions are natural questions for uh
complexity theorist. uh how does two
resources relate to each other and
whether they they can trade off or maybe
you can minimize them both at the same
time. Uh and uh it depends on the
problem. There are there are problems
for which uh we know results like
multiply time and space it has to be at
least the square of the length of the
input. So you can either do it with very
small space like logarithmic space but
you need to pay maybe quadratic time
and uh if you want linear time you have
to pay linear space or close to linear
space. There are results of this type uh
in in various models of computation.
That's another thing you play with. Not
all of them are you know they are all
equivalent in principle but if you care
about exact time or exact space are not
equivalent. So there are problems for
which there is a tradeoff there are
problems for uh you know where you can
solve them in linear time and
logarithmic space. One very important
general result that is a breakthrough
from last year is a result of Ryan
Williams. Uh and I'll tell you what it
is, but I first describe what we knew
about time and space. There's a clear
inequality, right? If you run in time t,
you will never use more than space t
because you never visit so many cells or
registers in your machine. So space is
at most time.
50 years ago valant Paul and Piper uh
improved this a little bit. They said
that if you run time t there's an
equivalent computation that will do this
in slightly less space than t t over log
t. That was a big result. Uh the running
time of course will blow up. it will be
very very expensive time-wise but at
least you can save on space a little bit
and uh this was uh believed almost 50
years to be the best you can do in fact
we had arguments that in certain models
in certain stylized models of
computation
uh you cannot improve that I not
describe you know this restricted models
but some natural restricted models
You cannot beat this.
And what Ryan Williams descri
found out last year is that in fact much
better can be done. Any computation that
runs in time t can be simulated by
another algorithm that uses only square
root of t space far far less than you
know before. And uh the algorithm is
quite uh uh sophisticated and uses an
earlier result of uh James Cook, the son
of Steve Cook of MP completeness and Ian
Mer that was you know an essential
technical ingredient but anyway uh you
can you know there's a a really
interesting uh way to to save space very
very non-trivial way to save space.
Again this algorithm will run in a lot
of time but at least you you have a
sense that uh yeah there the two
parameters are related in a highly
non-trivial way.
>> Is this for a a general problem or
>> general problem for touring machines?
>> Okay.
>> It may not work on random access
machines or Yeah. What's the the trick I
if you could explain intuitively or is
it too deep to explain in
>> it is
you know really technically explaining
it it's too deep but let me I'll give
you a much earlier result which sort of
indicates that really mysterious things
can be done in small space.
uh again it's uh probably yeah over 40
years ago people discovered the
following Dave Barington discovered the
following really interesting uh
phenomena. So suppose all you want is to
count. I give you a sequence of bits and
bits and you you want to count. You say
you want to know whether there are more
zeros than ones like the majority
problem. Who wants the vote? Zeros or
ones. Okay. Well, you can count. You can
just add them up. And this takes
logarithmic space.
And it seems that the best you can do. I
mean you want to count up to n
to represent n takes login bits right I
mean whatever n or the sum any number
between one and takes login bit it seems
essential
it turns out that there's an algorithm
I have to define exactly how it works it
um I I will not define let me I will not
define exactly how it works but it solve
this problem in constant space. It seems
like you can count arbitrarily high.
All you need is access to whatever bit
you like whenever you like. I want the
17th one. I want the 81st one. I want if
you can uh have random access to the
bits, even if you have constant space,
you can tell whether there are more
zeros than ones or ones and zeros
regardless how long the input is. The
trick is that somehow you use
non-commutive algebra. You use something
you know non-commutive algebra is not a
because everybody's familiar with
non-commutive things. I mean you we
usually put the cars behind the horse
and not in front of the horse. It
matters or in software engineering we do
this before that or it's very important.
The order of things matter. uh uh so you
can think about uh uh
applying permutations one after the
other you know if I rotate
a circle and then take a mirror image it
will give me the so these are two
permutations right I mean say I have end
points in a circle can shift it by one
or I can uh you know let's say flip it
around some uh diameter
There are two permutations and and they
don't commute. I mean if I first flip
and then rotate I'll get something else
if I first rotated and yeah think of all
the points as colored by yeah so it's
they don't commute. Bington is using uh
you know he's somehow encoding the bits
in the input by permutations
not large permutations permutations of
size five and somehow when he sees a one
he maybe rotates and when he sees a zero
he flips and the non-commutivity of this
um u of these operations
allow me to carry out a general formula
a formula of ns and os and knots you
know uh any formula like this formula
that uh let's say of some size s uh it
allows him to carry out this computation
to really simulate the ends and os and
not in this uh formula by rotations and
flips of this uh you know five
side sided pentagon Okay. And uh so just
to remember the configuration of this
pentagon, you need I don't know five
bits or right. So you need constant
space. How this captures the you know
the computation? I can tell you you know
one more sentence maybe it will not be
uh clear to um
everybody but
you this non-commuting things
uh you can you can do the following type
of operation
uh do rotate do flip then rotate back
and flip back. This is called the
commutator and it it can simulate an
endgate
the you know I can
it's too much to describe in words
without a board how it does it but
there's a very famous analogy which is a
riddle uh which if nobody I mean it's a
good riddle to to think about uh which
really captures this uh endgate problem.
You you want to hang a painting in the
following way. You have a painting uh
it's the it has a string connecting the
the two side but you want to hang it not
on one nail but on two nails. Okay.
There are two nails on the wall and you
can do with the string whatever you want
and the property you want
is that if the two nails are there it's
hanging every everybody's happy. If you
pull out one nail doesn't matter which
the picture falls to the floor.
How would you loop the string around
these nails so that you know this
happens? Clearly this is an end gate or
an O gate. Right. If one Yeah. And this
has to do I mean if anybody finds a
solution they realize what
non-commutivity I'm talking about. And
uh yeah it's a nice middle. Anyway so
this type of trick where you can really
um um this type of result you can really
do uh in small space things you wouldn't
imagine possible. It's a striking
example. It's really when I heard this
result first time I was the postto
um and somebody told me uh uh and I just
didn't believe it's possible. I mean you
cannot count arbit high with a yeah. So
yeah so the the trick that cook and
merits have in their algorithm is a
solution to a natural problem in much
less space than you would think
uh and uh it uses
some sense tricks of this nature.
So if you're counting arbitrarily large
that is information and you're saying
like maybe the intuition is that
information is encoded in the sequence
of operations. It is encoded. Yeah, of
course you are not you are not
delivering the final count. You just say
whether there are more zeros than ones.
If you have to write down of course you
need if the answer takes
some number of bits long then you need
this this number to write it down. If
you have a decision problem say like yes
or no like are there more zeros than
ones then you can do it for any any size
input in constant space. Yeah
>> that's incredible.
>> It's pretty pretty incredible. Yeah. And
by the way, this is a highly applicable
result. It's used in cryptography in a
fun in fundamental ways. It's useful.
Yeah, it's used in various places and
it's yeah, an extremely useful result
here. By the way, unlike the Ryan
Williams result, if you have a formula
of size S, you can do it in constant
space and the time of this algorithm
does not blow up really a lot. It's just
quadratic. So it's quadratic time. So
this is something actually doable,
useful, efficient and yeah, and it's
also magical.
>> We talked about the equivalence between
um these MPMPlete problems and then I
know in practice a lot of people to
solve the other problems they just use
SAT solvers.
>> Yeah,
>> I would have thought that would be less
efficient though because you got to kind
of translate it and then you're doing it
in almost like a different problem
space. Yeah, you you usually also
enlarge the instance. Usually in
translation you enlarge the instance. So
what your question is why do people use
cell service? I would say that uh
there's no problem other than
satisfiability that people uh uh thought
so hard about
really uh optimizing the huristics
that uh efficiently work on many
instances. There are very very clever
ways in which you can um you know try
start I mean you are not going to guess
all the end bits but you want to start
by guessing some bits that seem more
pivotal that if you like in dominoes
maybe when you set them to one value
they force many other many other other
values to be set and if that happens you
cut down your search space. So there are
many heristics of this type and also
more clever than this that allow to
solve such liability problems. If they
have such structure again the worst case
it will not will not help you. There is
in fact a conjecture
uh this is much stronger somehow than
npmpleteness
uh you know np complete problems taking
exponential time. He said that uh we
don't expect
any savings. We we expect satisfiability
problems to require really uh two to
some constant times n. It's not it's not
going to be two to the square root n or
or n to the log or something like this
is you know so yeah. So but the worst
case may be hard but people optimize
uh attacks on many many such formulas
that somehow have all sorts of
structural properties arising maybe in
practice and I think that's the main
reason that uh they are used it's also
convenient I mean uh it's very you know
people do it for uh testing
specification that programs protocols
meet specification. They're usually the
specification are usually easily
translated into simple constraints and
that's almost a susceptibility problem.
>> We talked about all the different types
of resources in an algorithm and in one
of your talks you said something where
you you consider randomness another
resource for an algorithm. What do you
mean when you say randomness is a
resource for an algorithm? In the early
70s,
of course, randomized algorithms existed
since antiquity and everybody was
tossing coins for lots of reasons and of
course statisticians
uh you know do sampling and use
randomness for but when when
algorithmics you know designing
efficient algorithms became big once we
have had computers uh people realized
that it can really enhance all sorts of
uh uh computation for example we had no
idea how to test primality of a number
and in the 70s uh both microabin and uh
survey and sass and found proistic
algorithms which are fast to test
primality okay so what does it mean a
probabistic algorithm it's an algorithm
that's allowed to make random choices so
you can think that there's an internal
uh you know little person or device
inside that tosses coins Of course,
that's not what happens. There's no
little person sitting in your laptop. So
the question is where do you get these
random bits? But it's very important to
stress that in all these um probabistic
algorithms, the underlying assumption is
that the bits you get are perfect. They
are half half each one and independent
of each other. It's like a uniform
distribution on all possibilities.
Now, where do you get this? I mean,
where seriously do you get this? I mean,
if you run a probabistic algorithm of
your laptop, since it doesn't have this
person inside tossing coins, it does
something.
Well, high quality randomness of this
type uh
costs money like time and like memory.
What do I mean by cost money? You can
have a very cheap solution. you can just
I don't know measure the thermal noise
in your computer or have one of the
Intel chips uh you know um you can
measure internet traffic and sample it
and believe it's random and and all of
these things are used you can do
something mathematical have some simple
procedure that is actually deterministic
like a linear congren generator
something like this and believe it's
random or you take can take the digits
of pi it's also So you know looks random
in some sense. So there are many things
you can use but you don't know they are
random. If you want them to be random
you know one source even this is not a
perfect source but we have quantum
mechanics. People believe you know
people believe it works in in life. It
seems like a cool theory of nature.
There are all sorts of arguments about
it but let's um put them aside. They
predict that if if you measure photons
coming out from some source and you
measure their spin whether it's up or
down, the prediction is that each one is
half half and it's independent of each
other. That's very nice. But if you are
going to build this device, it's going
to cost you a lot of money
and let alone that it will not be
perfect. But let's leave this aside
anyway. Since you want high quality
randomness or you have some way of
guaranteeing I mean you are running it
really on your laptop you it's not you
know okay the paper was written we can
test primality with probabistic
algorithm now we want to run it what do
you use so it makes sense to ask lots of
questions about randomness but to
guarantee the quality of the randomness
um and maybe you can minimize the is the
use of randomness by the way another
issue with randomness is that
you know the outcome is a random
variable and it's not always correct
right the whole point in most of these
algorithms you just have some small
probability of error if you have a
deterministic algorithm there's no error
so you also don't like the error so
treating it as a resource is simply a
convenient complexity theoretic way of
saying how do we understand you know uh
the amount of this resource we have to
invest or the number of bits we have to
invest
their quality and so on. So it's uh yeah
it's it's almost automatic for if you
think like a like a complexity theories.
How do we minimize for particular
algorithm like primarity testing
you know do you really need this? Do you
need them to be independent? Maybe you
can generate them in a you know maybe
you can you need n bits but you can
start from square n bits or from log n
bits that are really random and make
from them in some deterministic way uh
you know sort of pseudo random sequence
you can call it which is a good name
actually uh that will for this purpose
of this algorithm will look as if it was
random.
If you could do that, you don't need all
these bits. You can use much fewer. And
this whole theory of you know reducing
randomness, dandomization, removing
randomness is a huge field. And uh
people are you know there there are many
u problems and many ways of doing it and
uh uh the story with primality is
actually fascinating. So I mentioned
these two algorithms that were invented
and people were wondering about the
deterministic algorithm for primality.
It's a problem that has been articulated
already by Gaus in the most you know
complex theoretic way you can you know
uh back in his days hundreds of years
ago and uh maybe 150 I don't know
he was asking for an indefatigable
calculator
of course is a person but
he wanted this to be efficient that's
bas basically what
uh was looking for a primality test for
large numbers because they really wanted
to know about numbers maybe only few
tens of digits. They wanted to know
whether they are prime or not. There was
no efficient algorithm. Anyway, uh you
can wonder about this survey s and
algorithm.
Maybe you can use less randomness or
structural randomness that you can
generate from fewer bits and nobody had
any good idea. And then in the early
2000s
Agaral Kay and Fenna
uh devised a different probabilistic
primality test and it's different. So
the analysis of randomness in it is
different and once you understand how
randomness is used,
you can maybe say ah we don't need to be
really totally independent bits. it's
it's okay if it has some structure and
then they found using number theoretic
ways uh a method to to generate this
pseudo you know pseudo randomly
generated from very few bits and that's
that's how the so often I don't know
often but sometimes deterministic
versions of probabistic algorithms are
discovered in simply understanding the
way in which the algorithm is using the
randomness understanding the analysis of
the algorithm
>> and saying okay it doesn't use all that
much
>> you you mentioned a few times the
quality of the randomness
>> how do you quantify the quality of
random bits
>> this basically a question about what
sudo randomness is and the general
answer is that it depends
uh you want
to fool a particular algorithm let's say
for primality.
So you want the randomness to fool the
this you want the al this algorithm not
to notice that you switched from perfect
randomness to something that's really
far less random has far less entropy but
the analysis works nonetheless.
Another algorithm maybe you need you a
completely different type of pseudo
randomness for it. There are there's a
set of examples of uh algorithmic
problems for which when you look at the
analysis they are much simpler than this
primality uh testing. When you look at
the analysis it seems to use not the
independence of all the n bits. You
really need only every pair of them to
be independent or every triple and
spaces of random variables which have
this property are much smaller. you can
generate them from login bits and so you
can fool them with this stuff. So the
quality of randomness there's a phrase I
like that it's the quality of randomness
is in the eye of the beholder
uh or in the computational power of the
beholder. You really need it to be just
as good as the tests that are applied to
it. You know you just want to be
completely pragmatic. You don't care
whether it's random or not. You just
care that an observer of a particular
structure or particular computational
power will not distinguish the
pseudo random distribution which have
may have less much less randomness in it
than the perfect one.
>> In one of your lectures actually you you
mentioned that and you gave a good
example and I was wondering if you could
um give the intuitive example of why
randomness is a function of the
observer's computational power.
>> Yeah. So I uh if you watch this talk you
know what the the example I give is an
example that's taken from this
fundamental paper of Manuel Blum and
Sylvia Malli. They tell you to consider
three experiments and the experiments go
as follows. They always between you and
me. You are the observer. I am the coin
tosser. I have a coin on my finger and I
toss it and just as it leaves my finger
you are supposed to predict what the
value will be when it falls on the floor
like in two seconds you have to
immediately say heads or tails. Okay
before you have to predict before it
falls. Uh well this is the first
experiment and uh you know what I ask
and what they ask you know what do you
think is a success your success what are
your chances of predicting it and the
obvious answer is you know one half you
know what uh how can it help you know
how what what can you do
the second is when you sit there but you
have a laptop like you have now and uh
yeah what what can you you will yeah I
don't know that you can how fast you
type, but the coin will be on the floor
in a second. The third experiment is
where your laptop is connected to a Cray
superco computer and the Cray superco
computer is connected to a bunch of
sensors and cameras and whatever devices
you want. They are all trained on my
finger.
Okay? And so as it leaves my finger the
coin the this apparatus certainly is
more than enough to calculate all the
you know angular momentum of the coin
and the distance to the floor and the
humidity in the air and whatever
parameters that completely determine its
motion in particular how it will land in
a split second far less than the time
needed to. So the the real point in this
example is
that the experiment the random cointos
this cointos did not change in all of
them. It is the same what you know
masses of people in math and physics and
philosophy and you know defined
randomness in various ways. There are
many definitions of of randomness and
they all focus on this event on the
cointos or sequence of cointoses. We in
complexity theory starting from this
paper
don't care about this event. I mean the
event stays the same and all it focuses
on the observer and it the only thing
that changed in these three experiments
is the computational power. So we want
to know how much enthropy is in the
coin. If you don't have enough
computational power, it seems to be full
entropy. It's a half half, right? You
don't know what it will be. If you have
enough computational power, you can
predict it completely and then it has
zero entropy.
So what changed is the observer. So the
observer is this algorithm we talked
about before. And uh any test that's
applied to you know uh to a set of to a
distribution to test the quality of
randomness depending on the test you
want to just make sure you you you want
to use as little true randomness uh in a
way that the observer will not notice.
And this is the source of many of the
important theorems that
um you know show that you can remove
remove randomness or reduce randomness
uh uh in probabilistic algorithms with
or without assumptions and uh uh really
are behind this understanding that we
have today. Randomness in algorithms is
not as powerful as we thought it is.
Like if if you know that something like
P is [clears throat] different than NP
or you have a hardware sing salesman is
exponentially hard or sus. If you know
that then in fact I can give you a sud
random generator that will dandomize any
probabistic algorithms. We know that
under this assumption we have what we
call P= BPP. Anything that has an
efficient probabistic algorithm also has
a probab
an efficient deterministic algorithm.
You just need to know that there is a
hard function somewhere. Under what
assumptions do we know P equals BPP? uh
the assumption uh the very natural is
that one of these NPR problems or in
fact even problems in higher classes
requires a lot of hardware require
exponential size circuits to solve okay
we believe that it's like P versus NP
strengthened you cannot cut down the
exponential search space
Um and uh so maybe people are you know
happier with with with this assumption
but this assumption about uh time
complexity it has no randomness in it.
It's sort of at first it's shocking uh
that it's actually related to the
problem of removing randomness from
algorithms. So that's one fundament
fundamental connection. It's this
hardness versus randomness paradigm.
But we know even more. We know that it
goes both ways. We know that if you are
trying to remove randomness for some
algorithms, if you can do that, then you
found the hard function.
So there's really a an almost it's not
an exact if and only if but
uh again and there are many variants of
this in some variants is if and only if
is stronger but we really know that it's
really one of the other and since it's
hard to believe that all these hard
problems are easy or the similing the
hard problem like P= NP we tend much
more to believe the other alternative
name is that randomness in algorithms is
weak and you can remove it.
>> Open AAI, Enthropic, Cursor, and
Verscell all use this product to make
their lives better. And the problem it
solves is when you're building SAS or an
AI product, and you want to sell to
other companies, there's all these
requirements you need to meet. There's
SSO, there's SKIM, there's arbback,
there's audit logs. These are all things
that take time to integrate, but aren't
the main focus of your app. Work OS is
an API layer that lets you meet all of
these requirements in just a few lines
of code. So let's say you have a new SAS
product and you want to sell to other
companies. Work OS will solve all of
these critical feature gaps for you. You
can check them out at workos.com to
learn more and get started. And I
appreciate them for supporting my work
and sponsoring this podcast. Is [snorts]
there an intuitive explanation for the
relationship between problem hardness
and randomness? Yeah. [laughter]
Yeah. There's almost always an intuitive
explanation for Yeah. So what's the hard
what's the hard problem? I give you the
input. You you are a limited computer.
You are a polinomial time algorithm. I
give you the input. Let's say it's a
traveling salesman problem or you don't
know the answer. So you there's some
entropy in the answer, right? It's in
the same sense we discussed before
there's some entropy tiny entropy maybe
exponentially small entropy because
maybe the you know if the input is
random maybe only few instances are hard
and all the others you can solve but at
least you see a hint of a relationship
between hardness and entropy. This of
course is not satisfactory because we
want half we want the you know we want
uh that for you the answer will be like
a cointos not like a very biased
cointos.
So we need to find ways to amplify
this uh uncertainty for you. They
amplify the hardness. We want not just
that some instances will be hard but
that the random instance
whether the answer is yes or no for
polomial time observer will be half you
will not be able to gain an epsilon
advantage over a random guess.
So for this there we developed all sorts
of methods that amplify amplify
randomness. Now this doesn't solve the
problem at all because I managed to take
you know n bits a random instance of a
problem and manufacture one bit that's
hard for you to guess but I could have
taken the first random bit I pick for
the so I generate from many a few one
what you want to do is the opposite you
want a method that will take a few and
we generate many
right that's a random generator So, so
the random generator starts for a few
truly random bits and generates many and
for this we need
we need other tools. Uh there's
something uh that I developed with
Nissan
because today the NW generator. I like
to say that you know people
say that making the f first million
dollars is easy and afterwards you can
make many more millions.
You can think of it this way. The
hardness in the way I described it allow
you to make $1 million. But once you can
make one, there are methods to make many
more and in fact more than the number of
bits you started with. But still their
quality depend on the hardness of the
function you use. we still use this and
uh your your limit you know limitation
of you know being running polomial time
so it's you cannot solve this hard
instance you build many many instances
from a short seed you you start from
maybe a logarithmically
uh long seed you take many subsets of
this like n you need n of them and I ask
you for the value of the solution to
each one. Each one is hard but we want
to say that they are simultaneously
hard. You cannot tell them apart.
There's no correlation you can detect
between them even though they're
extremely correlated. So yeah, so we
have methods to do that as well. So
that's the connection you embed having a
hard problem to a limited observer means
that some uncertainty about the answer.
That's a key that's a starting point. So
when you say that the quality of the
randomness is a function of the
computational power of the observer, one
thought that comes to mind is imagine I
have um maybe infinite compute then then
nothing is truly random. Is that is that
accurate to say like you know if I had
infinite compute I the weather is not
random nothing is random. Uh okay. So
it points to the fact that you have to
really be careful about what question
you are asking about the randomness if
uh you want uh you know u to apply this
to to probabilistic algorithms
then it's really important that you are
limitless computationally. So if you
have infinite compute times you will be
able to distinguish
a a distribution with full entropy to
the random and one with coming from a
generator one with low entropy. So you
could do that but one thing you cannot
do with infinite compute is something
that's information theoretic. So there
are many other uh things we need to do
with random bits than just run probistic
algorithms. For example, we want to
generate passwords for our you know
crypto you know for uh security systems
there the very demand is that they are
random right I mean Shannon theorem
tells you you know the quality of your
passport is as good as the entropy in
it. So uh the notion of a cir secret
rests on the random on the true
randomness of the so if I just ask you
to produce a random beat or you ask me
to produce a random beat uh you know
whether you have computational infinite
computational power or not doesn't
matter I mean to generate this random
bit it has to be random I mean you your
demand is not that it will succeed in
some test you really want the
probability of heads to be half, tails
to be a half. This you know then this
definition or this task of producing
randomness
is not related to your computational
power.
So you know lucky or unlucky I don't
know for us many times we do have
implicit or explicit tests for this
randomness you say I can break this you
know I can break this system or
something and then you can maybe use to
the randomness but uh if your very
demand is to have a random event then
you need to produce a random event. I
saw in when I was doing my research that
there are ways to uh create higher
quality randomness by aggregating weaker
sources.
>> Yeah.
>> Um how how does that work?
>> Well, it's another theory. I talked
before about the theory of pseudo
randomness. There's a whole different
theory. They are related in non-trivial
ways, but uh um it's called the theory
of randomness extraction.
and or randomness purification maybe and
this is exactly what you asked about. Uh
we imagine that the world maybe does not
give us perfect randomness. But we have
all these events we cannot predict like
the weather uh or or various quantum
phenomena or sunspots or we cannot
predict the you know stock prices right
otherwise the market will be but these
are not you know even though these are
these are unpredictable events they are
somewhat predictable. I mean the weather
tomorrow is more likely to be similar to
the weather today than the opposite of
the weather. So there are correlations
if you sample this weather for example.
There are also biases. I mean sometimes
you you know in the spring it's more or
in the summer it's likely more likely to
be hot than cold.
So there are biases correlations. These
are called weak random sources and
there's a mathematical quantification of
uh how weak they are basically talk
about the amount of entropy in them. you
have n bits potentially you can have
entropy n but maybe they were generated
from a generator or they came from some
source of we don't know uh so it has
some entropy in it but you have no idea
where I mean maybe half of them are
fixed and half of them are cointosis and
you don't know which half maybe they are
each you know half you know three
quarter zero and one quart of you know
So tails have a bias that also has lots
of enthropy but not full and maybe the
correlations are even more complicated.
So you can imagine all sorts of
situation like this and you
mathematically model it by saying okay
there are n bits it's a probability
distribution n bits which has some
entropy let's say square root of n you
don't know where and uh you want to use
it in a probabilistic algorithm. So it's
a basic question. Can we use physical
events
uh weak sources coming from nature maybe
uh in in probabistic algorithms and
certainly not obvious. I mean just
feeding them to the algorithm as is not
going to work. They are very easy to
find simple algorithms that will fail
that will succeed on perfect randomness
and will fail on will always make an
error.
But uh the theory of randomness
purification wants to take this
um this um uh sample of n bits with all
with some amount of entropy which is not
full and someone massage it create from
it maybe a shorter string which is u you
know of higher quality. Ideally it would
be perfect random bits. So ideally you
can imagine that if I have n random bits
and I have enthropy root n maybe I can
massage out of there square root n or
maybe just the fourth root of n
bits that will be essentially uniformly
distributed then if I have an algorithm
that just needs this amount that's what
I feel it turns out you cannot do that
it's impossible but what you can do is
not produce one string of length let's
say square root 10 but you can com you
can produce n to the hund of them
okay and what you are guaranteed so this
is a this randomness purification uh
device is an efficient algorithm that
takes any any uh distribution with
enthalpy in it and you produce many
blocks polomally many blocks of the
length roughly the enthalpy what you
would hope to be perfect and what you
are guaranteed is that 99% of them are
truly perfect. So you have many
99% of them are as good as perfect and
there's 1% which is bad. You don't know
which it is. But that's already solves
your problem because run your algorithm
on each one of them. take a majority
vote. Doing this is extremely
complicated. There are many ways of
doing it. There are varants of you know
various assumptions you can make about
the entropy. Maybe you have several weak
sources that are not related to each
other. There are various
um uh yeah the various variants and this
theory is very well developed. But we
know that uh uh the statement I made
essentially is is accurate. If you have
one source uh with some entropy in it,
you can generate polomially many samples
of the length of almost the entropy and
most of them will be perfect. So that's
as useful as having one. Yeah. I vaguely
remember I was skimming a bunch of
papers and one of the papers it had this
uh had this figure where it was a
two-dimensional array of numbers and I
think there were like drawing rectangles
or something like that. Is that like one
of the ideas? Uh so it's a notion of
pseudo randomness which is related to uh
one particular variant of this
extraction problem where you have
several weak sources not one one is the
hardest because that's yeah but maybe
you have a few that are independent and
each of them has some entropy in it
and uh I think what you're referring to
is this sum product theorem this uh uh
yeah I cannot draw the pictures of there
but uh you don't really need to. So
let's just think about this problem. You
have uh uh three sources of randomness.
They are each weak. So each has just a
little bit of entropy in it. And all you
want to produce is one source with
somewhat larger entropy. So you are
losing in the number of sources but you
are gaining entropy. If you can repeat
this, you eventually get to full
entropy. So that's the idea. So what how
what combination of weak sources would
you take? It's not obvious and the
solution. Yeah, this is a certainly
there is maybe even this one. Uh there's
a paper I have with Barak and Impalato
about this particular problem and we are
using a result in what's called the
arithmetic combinatorics and I can
explain it very simply. I think that we
learn about addition in second grade and
about multiplication third grade maybe
and you know the only motivation for
multiplication is that it's a way to
shortcut repeated addition
and that's all we talk about. Then if
you go to college you you learn that you
know sum and products are the basic
operations of fields. You can do it with
integers. You can do it with rational
numbers, complex numbers, finite fields
and so on. So you remember these are the
basic but how do they relate to each
other?
It's not clear. It's not maybe there are
many ways to ask this question but one
way to ask this question that was
suggested by Erdesh and was
solved the first time by Erdish and
Seamar and then in a much more in a form
we really need by
Kent to say the following just think of
a set of integers
and add all pairs so you start with
let's say K integers add all pairs how
many new integers Do you get this you
should think of as entropy increase if
you get many more somehow? Yeah. So you
have K integers. Well, it depends what
they are. I mean if there are the first
K integers and you add all pairs up, you
get just the number between one and 2 K.
That's not much larger. That's a factor
or two larger. If you want increase an
entropy, you want to get you know uh
some power of k bigger than one.
Of course, if you take a random set of
integers,
uh you'll get k square, they will all be
distinct k² integers. So somehow you
want to say I mean it would be great if
for any set when you take all pairs you
group but it's not true by this example
of the interval. Well, you can not take
sums. You can take products.
Okay? But also products don't always
increase. If you take, you know, one,
two, four, eight, you take a geometric
progression, you multiply all pairs,
you'll just get just twice as many as
you start. So that's uh it's also not
good. And uh the magic in this sum
product theorem is that
sums and products are orthogonal to each
other. Somehow if one of them fails to
grow a set then the other will grow this
set.
And so this is an amazing result and the
way you use it in this context you think
of the outcome of your sources as
numbers.
you let's say multiply the first pair
and add them to the third you mix the
sum product. So this guarantees even
this is not obvious but if you do this
it guarantees that you you grow the
number of different values you get is
significantly more than K maybe it's K
to the 1.5 or something entropy does
increase and that's that's the source of
you need to prove it distributionally
it's not just the size the entropy is
not just size
um along with the size it's more than
that but anyway this is behind one
solution to one of the problems about
purification. It does not solve the one
source problem. This you need other
tools.
>> I saw that um you had done some work in
zero knowledge proofs. I was wondering
if you could explain you know what is a
zero knowledge proof and maybe we talk
about its significance.
>> Sure. Yeah. Z knowledge proof it's
pretty amazing that it became a
household word. I mean it was in the
domain of theorists for a long time. Uh
the original definition of zero
knowledge proof came in a paper seminar
paper of
uh Goldster Mi and Rakov
which also contained the definition of
interactive proof. So even before zero
knowledge uh they conceived of the
notion that proofs don't have to be
written down like in mathematical
papers.
people can have a discussion a
randomized discussion in which I'll try
to convince you of something or I I want
to prove to you something like I know
the uh you know the proof of the Roman
hypothesis or I can solve this suduku
puzzle and uh we can do it interactively
with the rand you know we are randomized
in particular you the verifier of my
claim are allowed to be randomized so
it's like in randomized algorithms but
Now the prover there's a prover it's not
just an algorith it's a prover like in
NP someone who knows the solution but
the convincing has this interactive
uh form so this model was suggested in
this paper and also in a paper of babai
parallel in the same time from different
motivations
uh
basically it offers a generalization of
the notion of np
is That's when I send you a message and
it convinces you. You verify it and it
convinces you. Now we allow an
interaction and we allow you you know a
small chance because you are randomized.
We allow small chance that you will uh
you know I will convince you of a false
claim but this error can be reduced like
in probabilistic algorithms can be
reduced arbitrarily. You want one in a
billion you can get one in a billion
whatever. Yeah. Anyway, so there's a
notion of an interactive proof and then
uh in the gold mali of paper they
suggested
another
notion of interactive proof which is
more restricted. You want to prove
something but the zero knowledge means
that you want the verifier to learn
nothing absolutely nothing about the
proof except that it's true.
Now this sounds really totally
ridiculous. I mean if you think about
the last time you convince somebody
uh to change their mind about anything
without providing them any any knowledge
any new things they didn't know. Say
what what are you talking about? This
such proofs don't exist for anything
there. No zero knowledge for anything.
Uh they were not thinking about you know
uh convincing someone of you know
political opinion. they were thinking
about cryptography of course you know
they've created the foundation of
cryptography in many in many other
papers um but they are imagining uh uh
cryptographic protocols in which you
have secrets and you you use these
secrets in your computation
and you have you know the protocol tells
you to do things that if you don't then
you know you're violating the protocol.
So the others don't want you to cheat.
They want to make sure you perform the
right operations on your secrets.
Uh for example, you are supposed to pick
a a public key by multiplying two uh
prime numbers. If you multiply three
or something else,
then you you are violating the protocol
and maybe security is not guaranteed. So
I would like to convince you that the
number I give you is actually a product
of two primes. I certainly don't want to
give you the two primes. So what I
really want to convince you of is that I
computed this number by multiplying two
primes. And you learn from this
interaction
absolutely nothing except you are
convinced with very high probability
that I did multiply two primes and not
any other number and I didn't do
anything else that I shouldn't have. And
you can think about lots of other
cryptographic protocols where people are
doing things like multi-party
computation very complex things they are
confusing with their secrets and they
don't want to reveal them whereas the
others want to make sure that they did
what they should. So there are any
number of you know applications to this
idea. The only problem is it sounds
ridiculous because it sounds impossible
in mathematics terms. If
uh you know some somebody came here and
said that P you know they prove P
different than NP you know I I would
want to see the proof and then tell me
okay I prove it to you in zero. How can
anybody convince me that they have a
proof of P different than NP and I come
out you know congratulating them and you
know
uh amazed by them and nevertheless I
know absolutely nothing about the way
they proved it. I'm I just know that
they did this. So it really sounds
ridiculous
and uh yeah certainly one of my favorite
papers maybe my favorite is the zero
paper which came a year later is joined
with Od and Sylvio Mikalli where we saw
that it's not only not ridiculous it's
universal
namely anything which has a proof a
mathematical proof also has a zero
knowledge interactive proof Anything
like P different than NP or that I
multiply two primes or anything that you
can prove revealing your secret you can
prove without revealing your secret and
convince beyond any reasonable doubt. So
that's possible.
>> What's the intuition behind that? Like
let's say I have a proof for P= MP and
we want to convert it to a zero
knowledge proof. How does that work?
>> How does this work? Well, first of all,
it assumes cryptography. So we assume we
have some oneway functions. We we assume
that some you know problem like factor
integers or this logarithm or any number
of oneway believed oneway functions uh
exist. So oneway functions if people
don't know functions that are easy to
compute in one way but are hard to
invert. For example multiplying numbers
is easy.
Finally the factors of a number which is
the inverse problem the prime factor is
believed to be hard of course we never
we can never we don't know any hard
problem that's the previous entry
question we don't know but we believe
about many problems and we the belief is
actually the whole world believe because
the whole world is using cryptographic
systems which rest on this all
electronic commerce assumes this so we
assume this so assume we
uh oneway functions uh oneway functions
allow you to uh create uh basically
garbled message commitments. I can uh
you know I have a number in my head I
don't want to tell you what the number
is. It's a number between one and 100. I
can write down another number
which looks like a random number to you.
And on the one hand you have no idea
I claim this encodes my secret. Okay.
And this commitment scheme which is
built very simply for one for monary
functions uh guarantees two properties.
A you cannot tell what is my secret even
though you can see this number this
other number I gave you. And uh on the
other hand I cannot change my mind about
my secret. It really commits me to the
uh so I can later provide you with a
certificate that I was thinking about 17
and I can only do it for 17. I cannot do
it for any other number. Okay. In fact a
very simple example is really using
factoring. uh in some sense the product
of two primes this number
uh you know it's easy you know this
number
uh commits it to its factors it uniquely
defines its factors right the only
problem is this is not exactly random
products of primes it's yeah but you can
do so you can do this okay so now uh
that we have to take commitments are
possible that's veryant important
uh so I'm I'm describing very high level
I'm hiding lots of things and even the
definition of zero knowledge the formal
definition is quite intricate it's not
the intuition is obvious and I said it
uh but actually formally defining is
non-trivial but at a high level I I'll
give you some idea about how a zero
knows proof looks like now we have to
think about what theorems am I proving
to you and it was very important to us
to uh figure out what problem to uh
think about even though today you can do
it for others but we were thinking about
uh theorems of the type here's the graph
we can color it in three colors it's
also a formal mathematical statement
either it's doable or not right and we
want we uh simply focus on proving in
zero knowledge claims of this type okay
the graph we both know I claim I can
colorize with three colors. You don't
believe me. You want to [clears throat]
be convinced of this fact and you don't
want me to cheat you. You don't want me
to be able to you know should be an
interactive proof and moreover we want
it I want it to be zero energy. I don't
want you to have a slightest idea of
what my coloring is or what anything you
didn't know before is okay. So roughly
the uh way it works the honor is proof
for this particular set of claims that
are certainly not all claims they are
very structured claims we look like the
following we iteratively repeat the
following procedure
I put commitments for the coloring
on every vertx I tell you you know I
don't tell you it's green red or blue
but I put a commitment to one of them on
each vertex.
You will choose at random an edge of the
graph and ask me to open these two
envelopes
to decommit.
And you will check that the colors you
see first of all are in this set. They
are not gray or orange. They are either
red, green or blue. And that they are
different.
This should give you some maybe slight
uh you know slight advantage or slight
uh support to the belief that maybe I'm
not cheating you. Of course, it's a very
limited one because I can cheat you in
some corner other. Yeah. So we have to
to establish two things. We will repeat
this again and again. We have to
establish that it's a you know that it's
a proof. It's an interactive proof that
I cannot cheat you. And we have to argue
the zon part. Okay. So let's do one at a
time. Uh to uh
do the the correctness that I cannot
fool you is very simple is the
following.
If the graph is not three colorable
whatever I commit for there's one place
which is an error. Either it has the
wrong color and not allowed color or two
colors are equal. you have some nonrival
chance of catching this with your random
guess right I mean it's one over the
number of edges not so small if you
graph on on you know with 100 edges it's
one in 100 if thousands if we repeat it
not thousand but 10,000 times the
probability that you don't catch me in
any of them drops exponentially to zero
right so
uh of Because there's a Okay, so this
this establishes that I cannot fool you.
The zeon knowledge is a more serious
problem because if I keep using the same
coloring,
you will ask me about this edge and this
edge and then eventually you'll know the
coloring of all colors.
Here's something that's really special
to the coloring that is being used. If I
have one coloring of the graph, I really
have six because I can peruse the name
there. I can replace red and green and
it's another valid coloring.
So what I do really in each one of these
iterations is not using the same
coloring but using a random one of these
possible six
that they are legal. They are all legal
and I I just use one of these six.
What's the advantage of this? when you
open a pair of vertices under this
distribution one of the six what you
will see if I do have a coloring and
that's the only I want to stress we only
have to establish zero knowledge if I
really can prove the theorem so if I if
I do know the solution the proof I want
to protect my knowledge
what happens when I reveal to you
two of these colors on the adjacent
vertices of the graph
It will be two in this distribution when
you restrict it to two vertices. It will
simply be two different random colors.
Right? This is what you get by all
permutations. This experimentation
what did you learn from this? Nothing.
You could have picked two random
different colors. You didn't need me for
that. So you didn't learn anything. So
in each iteration you learn nothing.
So this is the idea of the proof. Well,
this is the the end of the proof that I
can you know that showing that there's
there are zero knowledge proofs for all
u graph coloring three coloring
problems. What about all the rimonite
processes and the previous npn factoring
and all these other things I want to
claim to you and prove with zero and
everything here is very simple. You use
np completeness. This is an NP complete
problem. Anything can be that can be
proved is really something in NP. Right?
This is the definition. So you reduce it
to three color. You prove it in zero
knowledge. And and the main point about
reductions in NP is that they don't only
uh convert the you know the yes no
answer in a consistent way that if this
sort of this sable but actually if you
have a a witness if you have a proof for
I don't know whatever it will become a a
a legal three coloring of the graph you
generate. So if you have a proof you can
also have the three coloring. is very
important that the reduction
also provides a translation not just
between the instances but also between
the proofs. So NP completeness theory
gives you for free that if you solve the
problem for graph coloring instances you
solve it for any you can prove anything
in zero knowledge.
>> So um with the zero knowledge proofs you
can never be 100% sure. No
>> okay but practically I mean
exponentially approaching
>> you can make you can make the
completeness
uh 100% namely if I do have a proof you
will be yeah there will be no error in
your but there is a slight possibility
that the graph is not three coloring not
three colorable and you will not catch
me you can make this exponentially small
you cannot make it zero
>> when I think of cryptography oneway
functions there's this idea of you
quantum computation that's kind of
changed uh complexity theory a bit and
>> big time. Yeah.
>> Yeah. And I wanted to ask your thoughts
on you know how quantum computation or
that model of uh computation is changing
uh complexity theory like what are the
big takeaways?
>> Okay, let me say what it is first of
all. I mean uh yeah uh quantum mechanics
is a theory of nature that you know
seems to be everybody believes and
accepts. So uh like with randomness we
can ask why not enhance computers with
you know this physical knowledge. We
allow uh our computers to operate in the
you know ways that quantum mechanics
dictates namely manipulate
bits in superposition using unitary
operations whatever this means but you
know according to the rules of uh
quantum mechanics and uh really strange
things happen in quantum mechanics I'm
sure many many people know because you
know you can there are all these
interference pattern turns you. Yeah, it
seems that uh you know you can uh u
basically you are working with
probability theory with negative
numbers. Events cannot uh you know
aggregate only they can cancel each
other and uh okay so it's a model of
computation. It's a generalization of uh
touring machines. In fact it's
generalization of randomized touring
machine. It's very easy to see that uh a
quantum computer is at least as strong
as a proistic computer. How do you see
it? You just measure the quantum bits
before you start. You measure them. This
what I mentioned about the photons in
the beginning. If you you have a some
basic superposition on I mean quantum
quantum bit if you measure it you get a
random bit. So because of that quantum
computers are at least as strong as
proistic computers. uh okay so it's a
model of computation and uh it was
suggested in the 80s fineman
uh and man and others
uh suggested you know letting algorithms
use these quantum mechanical operations
mainly in originally for just simulating
quantum systems rather than building
bigger apparatus to yeah like we
simulate other things turbulence I don't
know what's the power of quantum
algorithms again let's say running in
polinomial time or efficient quantum
algorithm can they do more than
efficient classical ones deterministic
or probabilistic and it wasn't clear for
a while and there were
a few examples that were very stylized
but were not for concrete natural
problems we care about and then in 94
Peter saw sort of Yeah, created an
earthquake or an avalanche. Uh he uh
found quantum algorithms that are
efficient, the factual integers and also
complete discrete logarithms. The two
most basic uh underpinnings of all
security systems that exist and this set
the world on fire, right? So uh lots of
people try to do a lot of things. uh of
course you know people want to you have
them these algorithms they implement
maybe they want to break or other people
skip the system. So as you know since
then billions were invested by companies
by governments by uh lots of people
trying to to build the technological
infrastructure and this is extremely
complicated. holding beats in superp
position is extremely complicated.
There's things that are called the
there's the noise. I mean when people
build classical computers like for noman
here in the
uh building next door u u you know noise
was one of the serious problems because
the bits were really in vacuum tubes and
uh they had to contend and in fact he
built a nice theory of uh classical
computers that have errors noise they
have to cope with errors some of their
components can be faulty but this today
is hardware you know has no errors to
speak of. We don't I mean there are
error correcting mechanisms but uh we
don't need them for classical computing.
Intel chips don't have you know I think
error correction in them. Hardware is
very reliable. When you move to quantum
there is this the coherence noise
in quantum mechanics everything depends
on everything. the world can influence
uh the computation in your laptop and uh
and protecting from this is very hard.
There are quantum correcting codes and
that's part of the solutions. That's
only one of the problems. Just holding
bits in superp position is hard and
there are many hard technological issues
and there's progress on that. So this is
one line of huge investment.
Uh the other line comes from
cryptography because of course everybody
should be worried right. I mean you know
forget quantum computers if tomorrow uh
I mean really tomorrow uh somebody finds
even a classical factory algorithms in
algorithm in polinomial time I think
there'll be chaos in the world because
nobody nobody can do any transactions
because most security systems still rely
on
um
and so of course uh we want to change
these
We want to change the underlying
assumptions of security. We want to rely
the whole revolution in cryptography was
that we rest cryptography on
computationally hard assumptions and
with this we build all the wonderful
public key systems and you know all the
magical things you can do with
under uh by assuming that players are
computationally limited.
uh but now if they are the the
adversaries are quantum computers
certainly they can break this assumption
you want to find other mathematical
problems computational problems
uh which are somehow hard even to
quantum computers.
So that's a the whole field this change
complexity theory and cryptography there
is an army of people who are just uh
trying to invent problems. I maybe
should stress one way functions are easy
to find. I mean most problems you most
processes in nature are not easily
reversible. You make an omelette from an
egg, you know, reversing this is
doesn't take the same amount of time.
That's the usual example of a physical
one function. But trap door functions
like factoring
problems for which from which you can
build public key systems and that's the
most really basic thing for electronic
commerce
uh are few. We don't know many. So we
know this I mentioned factoring discrete
log in the 90s
it and created this another type of step
function from uh problems on latises in
high dimensions I will not describe it
but it's another problem and then people
refined and got a few more similar of
similar nature and it turned out when
Peter Sh discovered this people
immediately tried to solve other
problems with quantum computers in Fact
even today we cannot solve too many
other problems with quantum computers.
These are special. The special thing
about them is that somehow you can
reduce them to finding periods in a
signal and periods is like fel
transform. A f transform turns out to in
exponential space but f transform you
can do somehow with quantum computers
with interference. the latis problems
and problems related to it some called
learning with arrows and similar uh you
know to this day nobody found an
efficient quantum algorithm for them so
there's no even theory forget building
quantum computers we don't know how to
solve them and so uh what the world is
not just complexity theory is the whole
physical world of you know uh security
systems
And also governments like the NSA,
you know, is you know supporting or you
know asking the world to produce
assumptions that may be resilient to
quantum attacks. And so this is a huge
change. There's a major change in the
interaction between computer scientists
and physicists which grew tremendously
since this discovery
and it's reached in in many many ways
that are not the the influence of the
algorithmic thinking of uh on on
physical theories including today
theories in quantum gravity, black holes
and so is immense and yeah we have new
sources of problems and new models and
complexity classes etc etc and uh
there's a a fantastic fantastic
interaction
um
and uh it's also in complexity theory
uh in that it turns out that you can
discover quantum algorithms and maybe
then dequantize them in special cases
like I mentioned factoring before the
randomizing
and so sometimes It's a way, it's a road
to discover new algorithms.
It reveals connections between problems.
It's it's extremely rich. But one of the
maybe most amazing consequences is that
people I mean we being what we are, we
make up models and uh study them. And uh
the interactive proofs I mentioned
before uh turns out that uh even before
quantum they were generalized to
interactive proofs with not with one
prover but with many provers which seem
to be you know weird but turns out to be
very important in itself because it led
to this PCP theorem. Then people said
okay let's allow quantum verifiers
quantum provers and see what they can.
So one amazing result which is about
five years ago is the acronyms. Of
course we have acquames for all these
complexity classes. It's MIP star equal.
You may have seen it maybe you didn't.
And it looks weird but I'll tell you
what what it says really. It says that
there is a weird really weird uh proof
system with quantum provers
that uh you know trying to convince
verifiers an efficient verifier and it
turns out you know you ask for which
problems can they do it? Forget their
own knowledge just convince. And it
turns out they can do it for the holding
problem for for problems that are not
computable. Things that are not
computable are verifiable
by efficient verifiers if the provers
are quantum and they are entangled and
whatever. But it's a weird proof system.
Very weird. But it does something that
looks totally, you know, ridiculous.
things that are uncomputable by any any
classical are verifiable in this
interactive probabistic sense by uh
efficient verifier.
So what I like to say in talking about
this is that it seems that the best
reaction, best hypothetical reaction of
anybody who hears this. Okay, you
complexity theorist, you you plain your
sandbox and you build all these sand
casters and make up all these models
that have nothing to do with anything
just because you can and you get once
you weird enough, you get weird enough,
you know, consequences. So one message
which I think is very powerful is that
this result has absolutely fundamental
impact on math and physics. It turns out
that it implies and this was already
done in the initial paper.
It implies resolution of well-known
conjectures in math and physics.
It turns out that the you know weird as
it is it's a new mathematical technique
to solve problems that nobody had any
idea famous problems important problems
that fields were dedicated to are
resolved by this result by the
techniques of this result. So you ask
the impact of you see the impact is
many generations over with for different
motivations and uh developments but all
of them following the methodology of
complexity theory of understanding the
power of you know composational models,
proof systems and so on has magically
led to such a consequence
and this is just we are in the beginning
of this right this type of proof
technique is now being explored and used
and there are more results you know
using this type of techniques to
longstanding problems pretty amazing
>> that's incredible yeah I mean in
complexity theory you know there's these
um what do you call them I guess like
ven diagrams of all possible problems
and you know the implicit assumption in
this picture is that these are these are
>> decidable problems
In some of these diagrams there's a
little in the corner there's a
>> unidable
>> undecidable ones and
>> unreachable. Yeah.
>> Right. And it's just uh I I can't I
don't even understand how you could
verify an undecidable.
>> It's a 200page paper. It builds on 10
years of understanding which is both a
lot of development in the quantum
algorithms and quantum proof systems
sphere but also relying on techniques
from classical proof systems which have
to do with coding theory and uh various
algebraic stuff that is used to prove
for example the PCP theorem that I
mentioned it's you know it's a huge body
of work and on top of this they all this
200page paper in which they had to
develop many more tools and uh yeah
there you have it.
>> Wow. I mean when someone produces 200
pages of such complicated work that
makes such a outrageous claim how how
does that get verified by people? It's a
very good question. This tool for any uh
mathematical result that is complicated
and of course you you know that uh um of
course proofs of PES NP and the Roman
hypothesis are are generated very
frequently but some of them were
generated by very serious people and
took a long time to refute in these two
cases.
Um
and uh but others like you know the
permanent proof of the poner conjecture
one of the clay millennium problem
million dollar problems was another one
like that and this took several years to
verify and fix small bugs in and you
know books expositing this proof were
written and eventually this particular
paper is uh is for some reason still in
the referring stages in the analys of
mathematics.
now probably almost six years it will be
done. You know it's it's robust in the
sense that already new papers were
written with this type of tools in fact
giving somewhat alternative proofs of
the same same statements and stronger
statements in order to resolve other
mathematical conjectures but yeah it's a
it's a serious thing and in fact the
original paper had a bug like the
original paper with FMA
by wires FMA theorem also had a bug and
it was fixed and this was fixed. This
was very early on just when it came out
very quickly uh fixed. So it's any any
mathematical claim uh you know your your
question is you know very important for
in general mathematics is a and
mathematical truth is a social construct
that's what mathematicians believe.
Maybe we are moving into a world in
which we have lean proofs of uh you know
we have formal way of writing proofs and
there you can maybe formally verify them
but uh anyway uh I think that this
community is uh is quite certain about
yeah
>> in complexity theory it's very
mathematical in nature when I read the
papers but obviously it has implications
in computer science what's the
relationship between math and computer
science to you?
>> Well, I think uh the theory of computer
science, my field, complexity theory,
algorithms, this theoretical side
uh is
really lucky to have these two parents.
It lives in both spaces. It uh it is a
mathematical field in the sense that
most of what we generate are theoreans
and proofs in the mathematic sense.
uh on the other hand it's related to
computation because the kind of
questions we ask ourselves the problems
we are trying to solve are motivated
partly motivated by and trying to
understand computation. So you can think
of theoretical computer science very
much like you can think about analysis
and algebra and topology.
There are notions you know in in algebra
you're trying to understand equations or
systems of equations
and uh in in analysis you are trying to
understand very generally speaking
inequalities
um and continuous spaces right so there
are there are these notions you are
trying to understand computation is one
of these notions you are trying to
understand what can you produce by an
evolution of simple local steps
uh to a given environment the input you
know and this can be uh you know
sequence of bits or it can be the you
know the DNA of a you know of a person
which is being you know you know from
which you produce proteins using
computation or you produce a new baby
using the evolution of you know
fertilized egg uh or the weather or you
know so computation is sort of
everywhere
and you we are trying to understand it
in in ways that are different as we care
about resources how much resources are
exerted in any uh such computation and
uh you know trying to model it try to
you know understand the algorithms that
they underlying natural phenomena. So we
live in both spaces. We have a lot of
input of problems and models from you
know industry technology
uh systems and so on and we have all the
mathematics that is uh you know so we
have the rigorous side coming from and
the aesthetic side I would say you know
like creating models of poof systems
because they are nice because they are
interesting because yeah not because
they are implementable necessarily. So
this uh living in these two spaces uh um
uh you know is extremely beneficial to
this uh theory of composition.
>> You mentioned earlier that some people
might have the perspective and of
complexity theory that it's kind of you
solving problems for problems sake. I
read in another interview you did that
you were never motivated by application
and then my natural thought was what
motivates you to solve all these really
tricky complicated problems.
>> Okay. So let me say one thing about your
the beginning of your question. It says
about solving problems. I think that
what we do more much more is modeling
things. I mean modeling things then give
rise to problems that you want to uh you
want to understand. So I think the
modeling part in the theory of
computation modeling various forms of
computation is a large part of uh
theoretical computer science manifests
itself in particular in cryptography
where there are models of you know
adversary in distributed computation.
There are many you know I think modeling
just asking questions is you know and
creating making definitions
uh is a very central part of the field
and it happens more than in mathematics
maybe because they are more ancient than
maybe definitions happened earlier but I
want to stress this that's a very
important thing for example we discussed
randomness and our definition of
randomness is totally different and it
gives rise to you know very you know
surprising and interesting practically
theorems. Okay. Uh now that we settled
that uh what what motivates me or what
motivates other people uh of course
everybody has their own motivation. I am
a product of computer science education.
I uh all my you know undergrad and grad
school and postto and everything were in
computer science. So I think that I uh I
suddenly uh am sorry that I didn't take
many more math courses because then I
wouldn't have to learn things later in
life. But uh that aside, I think that
the focus on computation which is what
computer science education gives you
different you know different systems and
different uh uh issues are of course
algorithms in databases and algorithms
in uh you know programming languages and
in fact famous algorithms uh in other
other fields there are models and
algorithms in so computation is
something that I'm interested
intrinsically I'm more over the years
realizing that computation you know the
field expanded to interact with all the
sciences and that computation happened
everywhere in various forms in physics
and biology and so on you know makes it
a fundamental object of study and for me
given the way I was brought up I guess
in particular is fascinating in itself
uh I know from just experience
that lot of the theorems We prove not
many but probably with much higher
proportion than in other areas of mass
are impactful in you know in the world
in the in real systems in security
systems in blockchains in the real
world. But that this side this
particular side of um seeing exactly how
you translate your algorithm into
into a system or your uh you know zero
knowledge proof. I I predicted when we
came up with a zero knowledge proof that
it will never be implemented because the
protocol that I described more or less
to you is very costly. I mean you want
to prove that I I'm producing a product
of two primes and I convert it to a map
and then I do all this complicated
procedure many times. So doesn't seem
that anybody would ever use such a thing
but I was wrong. I mean I I didn't
realize how motivated people can be and
how important applications of zero
knowledge can be in the real world not
in theory of protocol design uh and they
did simplify maybe other using more
assumptions
uh different assumptions there's a
recent breakthrough of a postto here
I elango you may have heard because it
got some publicity in front and so on
where he introduced into The assumptions
of cryptography not just hard
computational problems but also uh
things of the nature of G theorem that
something is unprovable in some you know
mathematical proof system like Frank
whatever mathematicians use some using
that they can get zero knowledge that's
non-interactive
you can get yeah it's an amazing thing
it's get you know things get richer What
I what I want to say is that um
again from experience I have 45 years of
experience of this working in this field
which have been fascinating. Uh
you know I I mentioned to you uh in the
email you know there's
extra benefits to this field. I think
the community is amazing. Not just that
it has so many brilliant minds and young
brilliant minds are entering the field
all the time [clears throat] but also uh
very lively and interactive and
collaborative and uh you know just uh uh
yeah many of my best friends are also
colleagues. So it's it's fantastic but
the understanding that the theoretical
understanding of many things that we uh
maybe ask ourselves for aesthetical
reasons that are mathematical that we
generalize something for generalization
sake which may not have a counterpart in
in industry. In fact, show us work on
quantum algorithms. You can say why why
do that? There are no quantum
computers. Maybe let's wait till
somebody built once and we understand
why you know. So no, the answer is no.
No, you should try to understand
whatever is natural for you to
understand. This field has already
uh you know maybe it was not clear 40
years ago but certainly clear now that
all you know that
lots of theoretical understanding is not
just productions of mathematical
results but because it is about
computation
it is meaningful
I don't know often enough or whatever in
in uh in the real world. There are many
many other examples besides crypto and
quantum encoding theory and you know the
field revolutionized coding theory
mainly because of the PCP theorem tools
needed for
so you know there are lots of examples
and this eventually went into systems
you know for memory schemes or whatever
look I'm interested in P versus NP this
is a question about impossibility
Right. This is a problem. We still
didn't get closer in this at least
certainly the the years I've been at it.
Uh we are not much closer to showing
hardness for anything. We don't know
that multiplication is harder than
addition. It's a basic question.
U so uh this this kind of question by
itself is certainly not practical. I
mean it's not clear. Well, it is a
little clear because if you find out
functions, maybe you can substantiate
cryptography on a theorem rather than on
assumption. But anyway, uh there there
are questions in the field that uh don't
directly relate and will not directly
relate to uh implementations of any
system.
But they are all part of trying to
understand what efficient computation
can do and what it cannot or when can
you minimize resources of some type and
when you cannot and how do different
problems relate to each other. Uh this
basic methodology of the field that
created some wonderful edifice and I
would say that we are still in the
embryo stage of understanding
computation. You mentioned a few times
in this conversation um you know some
people made a major discovery and then
it you know kind of broke some
assumption that was maybe 50 years ago
and um you know researchers make these
advances and I know in your career
you've made a few as well and the time
space between payouts is sometimes
decades you know where you make a major
>> sometime
>> because a lot of people's career is like
maybe you know if you're just an
engineer you just you got your ship
shipping projects every year.
>> Um, but in in your case, like let's say
you imagine you discovered P equals MP
or something like that.
>> Yeah. How like how do you feel when you
make those discoveries, those sparse
discoveries in your career?
>> Well, it's great. [laughter]
Yeah, it happens. The big ones happen
rarely. uh I think of science I mean
realistically science and math is a you
know a community of ants work I mean
most progress we have this conferences
theor conferences
uh stock and forks and then we have all
sort of uh you know satellite
conferences and there are hundreds of
papers in them satellite I mean focused
on concrete area learning theory crypto
I know online algorithms you there are
many many there are thousands
researchers are working in this I don't
know maybe and uh they are producing
many papers a year and most papers are
and most of my papers are you know we
make a little progress in understanding
something usually it's not a big problem
you know we discover a variant of a
technique or we can strengthen a bound
on some
and I find this essential I think this
is true in in science in general
And uh bigger understandings come more
early and they uh suddenly you know they
they send the shock wave to everybody
learns them and uh and uses them. But of
course you know uh those bigger
understanding it doesn't have to be a
resolution of 50 years old paper. it can
be something that you know when barring
discovered his algorithm for counting
that I mentioned
he was trying to actually prove that
it's impossible
and it was not like somebody asked this
question the answer was obvious it's
impossible right so when you have an
insight of this this type it's uh you
know amazing so whenever you you realize
something really new for you and and you
know for the communities is a phenomenal
result. It's rare. I tell all my
students and posttos that yeah it's not
uh you know you don't work for the
million dollar. A million dollar is
nothing of course for this some of these
problems. Uh but yeah you you work
because you enjoy the practice of it.
You enjoy thinking about these problems.
In fact, most days in the life of my
life, mathematician's life is unlike a
systems person. You go in the morning,
you come back in the evening and you
fail to do what you wanted to do. You
just couldn't you just thought more and
yeah and I think that uh it's really
important. It's not so it's not for
everybody
clearly. It's not satisfying if you you
know this happens every day and every
week and you know uh it's not for
everybody but uh you know you uh it's
for the people who for whom this
activity of trying to think of throwing
ideas or failing but learning from the
failures people don't realize that often
you learn I mean the fact that you
failed is is not just a wasted day there
is something that you gain from is maybe
subconsciously that will help you later.
So unless you enjoy this activity maybe
this field is not for you
and uh yeah and then you see something
and that's even if it's small sometimes
it's very satisfaction.
Last question for you and I think you
know people in the field might be
curious because you have so much
experience is you know if you could go
back to the beginning of your career
when you just started you know becoming
a researcher is there any advice that
you'd give yourself?
Uh I think I was lucky enough not to
think that I would change anything. I
think I was lucky enough and many people
are lucky in this field because the
field is uh so so accommodating to young
people. there's uh it's completely
leveled uh you know there's no
hierarchies people would go to
conferences and meet I remember my first
conference meeting Darp who was you know
uh go in in the field and invented you
know did all these complete things and I
[snorts] was a first year graduate
student and somebody introduced me to
him and he immediately asked me what I'm
doing and I said I prove that some some
problem was NP complete and he was
actually interested
me. I I was lucky to have phenomenal
mentors as an undergrad as a graduate
student. I was lucky to have
unbelievable collaborators over the
years and you know you learn from uh uh
all this. So uh
it's not a very informative advice to
people to tell them to be lucky. uh I
think this environment exists. I think
that one piece of advice I I give
everybody is that uh uh in the early
stages is uh to work on things they
enjoy the most. So when you are
discovering your talents as a researcher
one one direction maybe you know these
are problems if you solve them then you
you but maybe that's not your problems
maybe it's not your affinity to them.
You have to experiment with the type of
problems. It's good to have a variety of
areas and papers to read in these areas
or problems to understand. It's always
good to start with a few to sort of
better understand your your capabilities
and often uh what you like most is what
you are better at.
>> Thank you so much for your time. I
really appreciate it.
>> Yeah.
>> Hey, thank you for watching this
podcast. If you liked it and you want to
see the show grow, please support with a
comment or a like. Also, if you have any
recommendations for people you want me
to bring on, please drop a comment.
Guests like Barbara Liskoff, Mike
Stonereaker, Mark Brooker, these were
all people that I brought on because
someone left a comment. On another note,
aside from the podcast, I'm working on
building the ergonomic keyboard that I
wish existed. Here's a glance at the
prototype. It's a split keyboard, so
there's two sides. Um, this is in the
case, but yeah, we launched on
Kickstarter and we hit our goal within 8
hours of launching. I really appreciate
it if you were one of the people who
grabbed one of the early units. Um,
we're now working on the long journey of
building the tooling now and so if you
still want to pick one up, I've left the
late pledges open on Kickstarter, so you
can grab one there. I'll put a link in
the description. Thank you again for
watching the podcast and I'll see you in
the next